Dr. rer. nat. Julian Q. Kosciessa

Lentzeallee 94, 14195 Berlin

kosciessa@mpib-berlin.mpg.de

ORCID: 0000-0002-4553-2794













I am an experienced researcher working at the intersection of cognitive, computational and systems neurosciences. My work aims to improve the characterization of neural dynamics, and clarify the functional role of neural rhythms and noise in flexible cognition. My experimental research combines neuroscientific techniques, and extends available methods via scientific open source software development.













بالأغرب الأخرى والأخرى والمرز والزري الأزري وأنس وأساله ويعتر والأطاع والمراجع ويرجع ويحران المال والاناف المتحدة

simulations

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Researcher

2020 - PRESENT

Max Planck Institute for Human

Development

Berlin, Germany

Predoctoral Research Fellow

2016 - 2020

IMPRS Comp2Psych

Max Planck UCL Center for

Computational Psychiatry and Aging

Berlin, Germany

Research Assistant/Intern

2010 - 2016

Berlin, Germany London, UK

Singapore, Singapore

EDUCATION

Humboldt Universität zu Berlin

2016 - 2020

Psychology

Dr. rer. nat. (summa cum laude)

Humboldt Universität zu Berlin

2014 - 2016

Mind & Brain - Track Brain

M.Sc. Master of Science

Freie Universität Berlin

2011 - 2014

Psychology

B.Sc. Bachelor of Science

SKILLS

MATLAB

R UNIX



Pvthon Git

Mandarin ____

KEY PUBLICATIONS



Kosciessa, J. Q., Lindenberger, U., & Garrett, D. D. (2021)

Thalamocortical excitability adjustments guide human perception under uncertainty **Nature Communications**



Kosciessa, J. Q., Kloosterman, N. A., & Garrett, D. D. (2020)

Standard multiscale entropy reflects neural dynamics at mismatched temporal scales: What's signal irregularity got to do with it?

PLoS Computational Biology



Kosciessa, J. Q., Grandy, T. H., Garrett, D. D., & Werkle-Bergner, M. (2020) Single-trial characterization of neural rhythms: Potential and challenges. Neurolmage

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

07/2020 - PRESENT **Postdoctoral Researcher**

Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany

10/2016 - 03/2020 **Predoctoral Research Fellow**

IMPRS COMP2PSYCH

Max Planck UCL Center for Computational Psychiatry and Aging Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany

Lifespan Neural Dynamics Group

Supervisors: Prof. Dr. Ulman Lindenberger, Dr. Douglas D. Garrett

10/2015 - 03/2016 Research Intern

> **UCL Institute of Cognitive Neuroscience** Pls: Prof. Emrah Düzel & Prof. Ray Dolan Supervisor: Dr. Dorothea Hämmerer

03/2015 - 07/2015 Research Intern

Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany

Center for Adaptive Rationality (ARC) Supervisor: Dr. Wouter van den Bos

09/2012 - 09/2013 **Research Assistant**

07/2014 - 09/2015 Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany

04/2016 - 09/2016 Cognitive and neuronal dynamics of memory across the lifespan

Supervisors: Dr. Markus Werkle-Bergner & Dr. Yee Lee Shing

01/2014 - 05/2014 Research Intern

Cognitive Neuroscience Laboratory, Duke-NUS, Singapore

PI: Prof. Michael Chee

Supervisor: Dr. Irma Kurniawan

EDUCATION

10/2016 - 10/2020 Humboldt Universität zu Berlin

Psychology. Dr. rer. nat. (summa cum laude)

10/2014 - 09/2016 Humboldt Universität zu Berlin

Mind & Brain – Track Brain. M.Sc. Master of Science (GPA: 1.0)

09/2015 - 04/2016 **University College London**

Two Erasmus exchange terms. Institute of Neurology

07/2013 - 05/2014 National University of Singapore (NUS)

Two exchange semesters. Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences

10/2011 - 09/2014 Freie Universität Berlin

Psychology. B.Sc. Bachelor of Science (GPA: 1.1)

TEACHING & TALKS

2022: Invited Symposium Talk:

Influences of arousal and cortical excitability on adaptive perceptual decision making. International Conference of Cognitive Neuroscience. Helsinki, Finland

2021: Research Talk:

The role of neural dynamics in flexible perception under uncertainty. Computational Neuroscience Symposium. Osnabrück, Germany

2021: Invited Research Talks:

Thalamocortical excitability adjustments quide human perception under uncertainty. Shine lab, University of Sydney, Australia Halassa Lab, MIT, USA

2020: Invited Collogium Talk:

Measurement and relevance of rhythmic and aperiodic human brain dynamics. Biopsychologie und Neuroergonomie. Technische Universität Berlin

2020: Invited Methods Workshop:

Multi-scale entropy as a tool to characterize neural signal irregularity. EEG Meeting. Max Planck Institute for Human Development. Berlin, Germany

2018: Invited Seminar:

Methods for the analysis of rhythmic and arrhythmic brain activity. International Max Planck Research School on the Life Course. Berlin, Germany

FUNDING & AWARDS

- 2021: DGPA Brain Products Young Scientist Award 2021
- 2021: DAAD Conference Travel Grant to OHBM Meeting 2021
- 2021: Merit Abstract Award OHBM Meeting 2021
- 2018: IBRO Poster Award Interpreting BOLD 2018
- 2018: DAAD Conference Travel Grant to Interpreting BOLD 2018 (Oxford, UK)
- 2015/2016: DAAD Erasmus Stipend (University College London, UK)
- 2014: DAAD PROMOS Stipend (National University Singapore, Singapore)

SUPERVISION

- 2021: Mentor at Neuromatch Academy
- 2021: Claire Pleche

M.Sc. student in Cognitive Neuroscience, Ecole Normale Supérieure de Paris, France co-supervision with Dr. Douglas Garrett

Professional Activities

Ad-hoc peer review:

PNAS, PLoS Biology, NeuroImage (9x), Journal of Neuroscience, Psychophysiology, Brain Topography, European Journal of Neuroscience, Mindfulness, PLoS One

- Member of the Organization for Human Brain Mapping (OHBM)
- Associate Member of the Deutsche Gesellschaft für Psychology (DGPs)

PUBLICATION LIST

manney My Manney Manney

Journal Publications (*corresponding author)

1. Kosciessa, J. Q.*, Lindenberger, U., & Garrett, D. D. (2021). Thalamocortical excitability adjustments guide human perception under uncertainty. *Nature Communications*, 12(1), 2430.

Higher-order thalamic activation increases when contextual uncertainty ambiguates which environmental features are critical for an upcoming choice, and is associated with switches from a rhythmic to an aperiodic processing mode.



2. Kloosterman, N. A., **Kosciessa, J. Q.**, Lindenberger, U., Fahrenfort, J. J., & Garrett, D.D. (2020). Boosts in brain signal variability track liberal shifts in decision bias. *Elife, 9.*

The magnitude of adaptive shifts from conservative to liberal decision biases under speed-accuracy emphasis is tracked by increasing signal variability in frontal cortex.



3. Kosciessa, J. Q.*, Kloosterman, N. A., & Garrett, D. D. (2020). Standard multiscale entropy reflects neural dynamics at mismatched temporal scales: What's signal irregularity got to do with it? *PLoS Computational Biology, 16(5)*.

Highlights and exemplifies biases in prior research using an information theoretic metric of signal irregularity and proposes avenues to adjudicate such issues in future applications.



4. Kosciessa, J. Q.*, Grandy, T. H., Garrett, D. D., & Werkle-Bergner, M. (2020). Single-trial characterization of neural rhythms: Potential and challenges. *NeuroImage*, 206, 116331.

Introduces a novel method that separates neural rhythms from background activity in magnitude, space and time, and enables specific rhythm characterization when boundary conditions are met.



5. Hämmerer, D., Callaghan, M. F., Hopkins, A., **Kosciessa, J.**, Betts, M., Cardenas-Blanco, A., Kanowski, M., Weiskopf, N., Dayan, P., Dolan, R. J., & Düzel, E. (2018). Locus coeruleus integrity in old age is selectively related to memories linked with salient negative events. *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 115, 2228-2233*.

Quantitative imaging indicates structural reductions in brainstem locus coeruleus integrity with increasing adult age, and links related noradrenergic drive to the encoding of salient events.

article

Monographs/Theses

6. Kosciessa, J. Q. (2020, Dr. rer. nat.). Measurement and relevance of rhythmic and aperiodic human brain dynamics. Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin.

This dissertation highlights improvements in the ability to selectively characterize rhythmic and aperiodic fluctuations, and discusses potential generating mechanisms as well as modulatory influences to contextualize their interpretation at the latent level of human brain function.

article

7. Kosciessa, J. Q. (2016, M. Sc.). Effects of short-term memory load and task training on the amplitude and abundance of rhythmic neural activity. Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin

Neural rhythms are dominantly characterized by their power, but this measure conflates amplitude and duration. This work separates these two parameters of human alpha rhythms and investigates how they are modulated during working memory.

8. Kosciessa, J. (2014, B. Sc.). The assessment of microsaccades from the rEOG. Freie Universität Berlin

Microsaccades are small, high-velocity eye movements. This work explores the potential to use visual EEG channels to detect microsaccades without an eye tracker, and describes adult age differences in microsaccade characteristics.

